Guide to the Sarah Ruhl Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Sarah Ruhl papers
1990-2017
YCAL MSS 1139
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
8.84
(10 boxes)
The papers include writings, teaching files, and other materials documenting Ruhl's career as a playwright and essayist and teacher of poetry, playwriting, and modern drama.
Ruhl, Sarah, 1974-
Arrangement
Arranged by type of material.
Sarah Ruhl (1974- )
Sarah Ruhl, born in Wilmette, Illinois in 1974, is an American writer of plays, poetry, and essays. Her plays include The Clean Room (2004), Passion Play (2005), In the Next Room, or the Vibrator Play (2009), and Scenes from Court Life (2016). Her plays have been produced on and off Broadway in New York City, in regional theaters throughout the United States, and internationally. Her book, 100 Essays I Don't Have Time to Write was published by Farrar, Straus and Giroux in 2014. She received a Bachelor of Arts degree (1997) and a Master's degree in playwriting (2001) from Brown University. She has taught drama and playwriting at Brown University and Wheaton College.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Box 9: (laptop): Restricted material. May not be seen without the permission of the appropriate curator.
Box 10: (hard disk and external hard drive): Restricted until January 1, 2068. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Sarah Ruhl on the Adele Gutman Nathan Theatrical Collection Fund, 2017.
Scope and Contents
The papers include writings, teaching files, and other materials documenting Ruhl's career as a playwright and essayist and teacher of poetry, playwriting, and modern drama.
American drama -- 20th Century; American drama -- 21st century; Authors, American -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 21st century; Dramatists, American -- 20th Century; Dramatists, American -- 21st century; Theater -- United States; Authors -- United States -- 20th Century; Authors -- United States -- 21st century; Dramatists -- United States -- 20th Century; Dramatists -- United States -- 21st century; Ruhl, Sarah, 1974-
- Writings, 1997-2017; 6; (6 boxes)
  - Plays
    Scope and Contents
    Each play is represented by printouts of draft scripts with and/or without autograph annotations. May be accompanied by production-related material including cast lists, rehearsal schedules, etc.
    - The Clean House, 2002–2017; 7 folders (Box 1)
    - Dead Man's Cell Phone, 2003–2007; 8 folders (Box 1)
    - Eurydice, 2003, undated; 7 folders (Box 1)
      Includes script with autograph annotations by "Les," and a Korean translation of script by an unidentified translator
    - For Peter Pan on Her 70th Birthday, 5 folders (Box 2)
    - How to Transcend a Happy Marriage, 2015–2017; 8 folders (Box 2)
    - In the Next Room, or The Vibrator Play, 2007–2008 June; 5 folders (Box 2)
    - In the Next Room, or The Vibrator Play, 2008 December, undated; 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Late, a Cowboy Song, 2002-2003, undated; 4 folders (Box 3)
    - Melancholy Play, 2003-2005, undated; 7 folders (Box 3)
      Includes printed piano and vocal score "cues" by Jeffrey Weeter
    - The Oldest Boy, 2014; 6 folders (Box 3)
      Includes cast and personnel list and other material from workshop production at Lincoln Center
    - Orlando, undated; 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Passion Play, 1997-2008, undated; 11 folders (Box 4)
    - Scenes from Court Life, 2015–2016; 5 folders (Box 4)
    - Stage Kiss, 2009–2013; 6 folders (Box 5)
    - The Three Sisters, 2009; 6 folders (Box 5)
      Biographical / Historical
      by Anton Chekhov; "English version by Sarah Ruhl"
  - Musical production
    - A Face in the Crowd, 2016–2017; 6 folders (Box 5)
      Music and lyrics by Elvis Costello; book by Sarah Ruhl; based on the short story and play for the screen by Bud Schulberg
  - Poetry
    Autograph manuscript and typed printouts of poetry
    - "1st Drafts--poems", undated (Box 5)
    - "Death in Another Country", undated (Box 5)
      Typescript prinout of volume of poetry
    - "Peggy Poems", undated (Box 5)
      Includes typescript printout short story, "Sorrow and Joy" by Peggy Munson
  - Short stories
    - "The Yellow Room," "Poor Deborah," "The Swim Club," and untitled, 2000, undated (Box 5)
      Includes printouts, annotated
  - Book
    - 100 Essays I Don't Have Time to Write, 2014, undated; 9 folders (Box 6)
      Published by Farrar, Straus & Giroux in 2014
      Includes printouts of manuscript and proofs with autograph corrections and annotations in an unidentified hand; printout of introduction to a reading of selected essays from the book
- Teaching Files, 1990-2002; 1.42; (2 boxes)
  - Brown University--Playwriting
    - Course packet
      - Introductory Playwriting, 2 folders (Box 7)
        Includes syllabi; reading lists; questions; and photocopies of essays on playwriting
      - Student work, 2001 (Box 7)
      - Student instructor evaluations, 2000–2001; 2 folders (Box 7)
      - Clippings for playwriting, undated (Box 7)
  - Wheaton College--Modern Drama
    - Teaching notes
      - Bogart, Ann
      - Brecht, Bertolt (Box 7)
      - Beckett, Samuel (Box 7)
      - Chekhov, Anton (Box 7)
      - Fornes, Maria Irene (Box 7)
      - Grimke, Angelina (Box 7)
      - Ibsen, Henrik (Box 7)
      - Kennedy, Adrienne (Box 7)
      - Mamet, David (Box 7)
      - Miller, Arthur (Box 7)
      - O'Neill, Eugene (Box 7)
      - Odets, Clifford (Box 7)
      - Parks, Suzan-Lori (Box 7)
      - Stein, Gertrude (Box 7)
      - Strindberg, August (Box 7)
      - Synge, J. M. (Box 7)
      - Vogel, Paula (Box 7)
      - Wellman, Mac (Box 7)
      - Wilde, Oscar (Box 7)
      - Williams, Tennessee (Box 7)
      - Yeats/Noh Drama (Box 7)
    - Photocopies of articles on playwriting and plays, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - [Anna Keepsakes?] (Box 7)
    - Berlitz (Box 7)
    - The Real/Mimesis (Box 7)
    - Other syllabi, 1990, 2001 (Box 7)
    - Timeline, undated (Box 7)
    - Student list, questions/papers, 2001 (Box 7)
    - Paper topics/guidelines (Box 7)
    - Student instructor evaluations, 2000–2001; 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Course packet--plays, 5 folders (Box 7)
  - Scene work--Piven materials, 2002 (Box 7)
  - Student work, 1998–2002 (Box 7)
  - Teaching poetry, undated (Box 8)
    Includes photocopies of published articles and poetry
  - Teachers and Writers
    - Printed volumes of student poetry, 1998–2002 (Box 8)
      Includes Blackstone Valley Industries Writer's group and Sophia Academy
    - Poems by school children, undated; 3 folders (Box 8)
    - PS 111--Project Read typescript journal, undated (Box 8)
    - Arts-in-Ed--other organizations, 1993-1998, undated (Box 8)
    - Sophia Academy (Box 8)
      Includes teaching syllabus and Ruhl's resume
  - Miscellaneous
    - Business card for spa (Box 8)
- Restricted Fragile Material, 1.0; (1 box)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted material. May not be seen without the permission of the appropriate curator.
  - Laptop (Box 9)
- Restricted Material, 0.42; (1 box)
  External hard drive and hard disk from laptop are restricted until January 1, 2068. For further information consult the appropriate curator.